Hi. For those of you who haven't seen dancing bears,
مرحباً. لأؤلئك الذين لم يروا الدببة الراقصة،
these are the dancing bears.
ها هي الدببة الراقصة.
In 1995, we started working on a two-year investigative research project
عام 1995 بدأنا العمل في مشروع بحث تقصي لعامين
to try and find out what was going on.
لمحاولة فهم ماذا يجري.
Because the sloth bears in the wild were obviously getting depleted
لأن من الواضح أن الدببة الكسولة في البرية بدأت تقل
because of this.
بفعل هذا.
This is the Qalandar community. They are a marginalized Islamic community
هذا هو مجتمع كالاندار. أنهم مجتمع مسلم مهمش
who live across India,
الذين عاشوا في الهند،
and have been in India since the 13th century.
وكانوا في الهند منذ القرن الثالث عشر.
We went about getting evidence of what was going on.
رحنا نبحث عن أدلة حول ماذا يحدث هناك.
And this is footage from a hidden camera in a button.
وهذه الصور من كاميرا خفية في الأسفل.
And we went in, pretending to be buyers.
وذهبنا، وتظاهرنا بأننا مشترين.
And we found this right in this very state, in Karnataka.
ووجدنا هذا في كل ولاية، في كارناتاكا.
And the bear cubs were being harvested from across the country
وكان صغار الدببة التي يتم اصطيادها من جميع انحاء البلاد
and being sold and traded.
ويتم بيعها والمتاجرة بها.
These were being sold for about 2,000 dollars each,
كان يتم بيعها بحوالي ألفين دولار للواحد،
and they are used for bear paw soup,
وكانت تستخدم لحساء مخلب الدب ،
and also being trained, later on,
ويتم أيضاً تدريبها، لاحقاً،
to become dancing bears like the one you just saw.
لتصبح الدببة الراقصة مثل هذا الذي رأيتموه للتو.
Sadly, the family of Qalandars depended on this bear.
بكل أسف، فأن أسر الكالاندريين تعتمد على هذا الدب.
The couple are barely 18 years old.
هذان الزوجان عمرهما فقط 18 سنة.
They already have four children beside them. You can see them.
ولديهم بالفعل أربعة أطفال بجانبهم. يمكنكم رؤيتهم.
And the economy of the family and their livelihood depended on those animals.
وإقتصاديات الأسرة ومعيشتهم تعتمد على تلك الحيوانات.
So, we had to deal with it in a very practical and sustainable manner.
لذا، توجب علينا التعامل بطريقة عملية جداً وإطار مستدام.
Now, when we started working deeper and digging deeper,
الآن، عندما بدأنا العمل بصورة أعمق والحفر أعمق،
we found that it's an illegal act.
وجدنا أن ذلك ليس عملاً قانونياً.
These guys could go to jail for up to seven years
قد يذهب أؤلئك الناس الى السجن لأكثر من سبع سنوات
if they were caught by authorities.
إذا تم القبض عليهم بواسطة السلطات.
And what they were doing to the bears was really appalling.
وما يفعلونه للدببة كان مروعاً حقاً.
It was unacceptable.
إنه أمر غير مقبول تماماً.
The mother bears are usually killed.
الدب الأم في العادة يتم قتلها.
The cubs, which are taken, are separated.
الأطفال، يتم أخذهم، وتفريقهم.
Their teeth are basically bashed out with a metal rod.
يتم ضرب أسنانهم بقضيب معدني.
And they use a red hot iron needle to make a hole through the muzzle.
ويستخدمون إبرة حديدية حمراء حارة لإحداث ثقب عبر الكمامة.
Now we had to start changing these people and converting them from using that
الآن ينبغي أن نبدأ في تغيير أؤلئك الناس وتحويلهم من فعل ذلك
for a livelihood, to getting something else.
من أجل معيشتهم، لفعل شئ آخر.
So, this is Bitu Qalandar, who was our first experiment.
لذا، هذا هو بيتو كالاندار، الذي كان أول تجاربنا.
And we were so unsure that this would work.
ولقد كنا غير متأكدين من أن هذا سينجح.
We weren't sure at all. And we managed to convince him.
لم نكن متأكد بتاتاً. ولقد رتبنا لإقناعه.
And we said, "Okay, here is some seed fund.
وقد قلنا، "حسناً، ها هي بعض بذور المساعدة.
Let's see if you can get something else." And we got the bear surrendered
لنرى إن إمكنك الحصول على شئ آخر." وتسلمنا الدب
to -- we set up a sanctuary. We have four sanctuaries in India.
الى -- إنشأنا ملاذاً. لدينا أربع ملاذات في الهند.
And now he sells cool drinks, he's by the highway.
والآن يقوم هو ببيع المرطبات، وهو بجوار الطريق السريع.
He has a telephone booth.
ولديه محل إتصالات.
And then it started, there was no turning back after that.
ثم بدأت، لم يكن هناك أي تراجع بعد ذلك.
This is Sadua who came and surrendered his bear.
وهذا هو سادوا الذي جاء وسلّم الدب خاصته.
And now he runs a cattle fodder store and a grain store
والآن يقوم بإدارة مخزن لعلف الماشية ومخزن للحبوب
near Agra.
قرب اقرا.
Then there was no looking back at all for us.
ثم لم ننظر الى الخلف بتاتاً، جميعنا.
We gave cycle rickshaws.
قدمنا عجلات ركشة.
We set up carpet-weaving units,
أنشأنا وحدات نسيج للسجاد،
vocational training for the women.
دورات تدريبة للنساء.
The women were just not allowed to come out of the community
لم يكن يسمح للنساء بالخروج من المجتمع
and work with mainstream society. So, we were able to address that.
والعمل مع بقية المجتمع. لذا، أستطعنا معالجة ذلك.
Education. The kids never went to school.
التعليم. لم يذهب الأطفال قط للمدرسة.
They only had Islamic education, very little of it.
يتلقون فقط القليل من التعليم الإسلامي.
And they were never allowed to go to school
ولم يكن يُسمح لهم بتاتاً بالذهاب الى المدرسة
because they were an extra earning hand at home. So we managed to get education.
لأنهم كانوا يكسبون زيادة في العمل اليدوي في البيت. لذا فقد رتبنا لتقديم التعليم.
So, we sponsor 600 children education programs today.
إذاً، نقوم برعاية برامج تعليم ل 600 طفل اليوم.
We were able to ensure brighter futures for these people.
أستطعنا تأمين مستقبل أكثر إشراقاً لأؤلئك الناس
Of course we also had to get the bears in.
بالطبع توجب علينا إشراك الدببة في الأمر.
This is what happens to the bears when they come in.
هذا ما كان يحدث للدببة عندما نستلمها.
And this is what we turn them into.
وهذا ما يحدث لهم من تحوّل.
We have a veterinary facility in our rescue centers.
لدينا منشأة رعاية بيطرية في مراكزنا للإنقاذ.
So, basically in 2002 there were
إذاً، عام 2002 كان هناك
1,200 dancing bears.
12 ألف دب راقص.
We rescued over 550 dancing bears.
قمنا بإنقاذ ما يزيد على 550 دب راقص.
We've been able to ensure better futures for the people and the bears.
وأستطعنا تأمين مستقبل أفضل لأؤلئك الناس وتلك الدببة.
The big news that I want to announce today
الأخبار المفرحة التي أريد أن أعلنها اليوم
is that next month we will be bringing in
أننا في الشهر القادم سنجلب
the very last bear of India,
أخر الدببة الهندية،
into our rescue center.
الى مركزنا للإنقاذ.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And India will no longer have to witness this cruel barbaric practice
ولن تشهد الهند بعد الآن هذه الممارسة الوحشية البربرية
which has been here for centuries.
التي كانت هنا منذ قرون.
And the people can hold their heads up high.
ويستطيع الناس رفع رؤوسهم عالياً.
And the Qalandar people will rise above all this cruel barbaric past
وسيتخطى الكالاندريون كل هذا الماضية الوحشي البربري
that they've lived all their lives.
الذي عاشوه طوال حياتهم.
And the beautiful bears can of course live in the wild again.
ويمكن للدببة الجميلة بالتأكيد العيش في البرية مجدداً.
And there will be no more removing of these bears.
ولن يتواصل إزالة هذه الدببة.
And the children, both humans and bear cubs
والأطفال، سواء البشر والدببة الكسولة
can live peacefully. Thank you.
يمكنهم العيش بسلام. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)